What if everyone in the world did
exactly as I said for one moment.
Anno Hideaki
The whole world, 4 billion people, doing exactly
as I say. But, that's not what I want at all.
I'm just trying to create the best work I can.
Direction of Neon Genesis Evangelion
When you're thinking of a path to take a story,
you start off with a full 360ยบ parameter.
To take the first step, you, of course, have to decide
to go somewhere within that 360ยบ parameter.
Let's say you decide north.
You stake a post there first.
Once that's done, you have another
360ยบ directional decision to make.
That's how I work.
The deciding factors for those 360ยบ
are the current situation, staff...
Money and time. It's all based on
the work environment at the time.
It's also a personal decision.
"Set and setting" as they say.
Think of highlighting a spreadsheet.
You decide your route, and with every
cell, you can see a little more of a path.
When you look back, it dawns on you,
"So this is how it comes together."
Rei and Asuka
There is a character for all kinds of fans.
A relationship triangle. It makes a triangle.
1 boy and 2 girls, one upbeat
and one quiet. It all splits.
For fans of upbeat girls, there is Asuka.
For fans of quiet girls, there is Rei.
There is also the hair lengths. Short hair
fans have Rei. Long hair fans have Asuka.
With that, we can get all of the fans.
That was the basic plan.
All that was left was the curvy girls fans.
Production Goals
Pride.
You want a sense of pride from your anime.
This is....
In the animation world, I would
go so far as to say I'm famous.
But, if I was to walk into
a bar and sit at the counter,
it's not a job I could easily use to strike up a
conversation with the girl sitting next to me.
It's embarrassing.
It's so embarrassing, it's not a topic
I want to bring up, so I gloss over it.
I guess that means I don't have much
pride in the anime I've completed.
It's embarrassing. It's under par work.
A misconception among anime fans is they believe
animation is popular media. It's not like that.
I'm still underground level.
Everyone that doesn't remain a major
player ends up branded as inferior.
Unless you're a big hitter
you're a nothing. It's shameful.
That's one thing I'd like to
get rid of in the community.
If I meet someone who has seen Evangelion,
I want to be able to say that I was the
director of it without feeling embarrassed.
That's pride.
If I'm talking to a stranger, I want to tell them
about my anime. Even though I can't explain it well,
when they finally see it, they won't
question it like, "What even is this?"
At the very least, I want them
to be glad they continued.
Our 30-year old target demographic
was the basis of Evangelion.
I want to increase people's pride. I don't
think anime fans have enough pride.
I know I don't have enough pride in my work.
If I can improve that sense of pride,
Ah, wait. I want to try making a film
that invokes that sense of pride.
I see it as a step towards normalcy.
The Future of Anime
Bleak.
Bleak?
No hope?
Bleak.
No light at the end of the tunnel?
It would be great if there
were light. Is there light?
I can't see it.
Could Eva be the light?
Eva has the power to step outside the box.
I was very conscious of that.
I wanted to get out of the box.
Even though I wanted to go out of the box, the
results show a slow retreat to seclusion within.
This isn't just a problem with anime. It's
something affecting all Japanese media.
It feels like the walls around Japan are quickly
blocking us in, and soon we'll have no escape.
It's a question of how far the courage
to take that leap out will take us.